<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Europes transactions discovered in a dialogue betwixt Democritus an English-man, Ernestus a German, and Landerlu a French monsieur</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3418A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31453</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11987760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11987760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38743)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1008:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Europes transactions discovered in a dialogue betwixt Democritus an English-man, Ernestus a German, and Landerlu a French monsieur</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51965:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Europes Tranſactions, DISCOVERED IN A DIALOGUE BETWIXT <hi>Democritus</hi> an Engliſh-man, <hi>Erneſtus</hi> a German, and <hi>Landerlu</hi> a French Monſieur.</head>
            <head type="sub">Liſenced According to Order.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Democ.</speaker>
               <p>TIS high time for me to put on my conſidering Cap, and leave Laughing, for theſe are ſad times, all <hi>Europe</hi> being as it were in a Flame,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſtus.</speaker>
               <p>Or rather in a dangerous Sickneſs, and (as the late King <hi>James</hi> ſaid of <hi>England</hi>) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; but the Country (God be thanked) has had a Royal Antidote ſince: But of all <hi>Germany,</hi> more than any Country, labouring under a <hi>French Diſeaſe,</hi> now and then hot burning Fits, French Plotches, even disfiguring the fineſt Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (Cities and Caſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) of all <hi>Europe.</hi> Firſt <hi>Heydleberg,</hi> which being the Seat and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the Electors of <hi>Palatine;</hi> where was a ſtately Seat, a famous Univerſity, and a ſtately Library: <hi>Manheim,</hi> the neweſt and regulareſt Place for Building (with the fine Castle <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riksbourgh</hi>) in <hi>Germany; Keyſerlauther,</hi> and now <hi>Spire,</hi> a large ancient City, as is alſo <hi>Worms,</hi> (though both <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Places) and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penheim.</hi> The poor People of <hi>Worms</hi> ſhelter'd themſelves in Caves under the Earth, but the <hi>French Furioſo</hi> drave them out with Cudgels, to others they ſunk the Ground, and ſo buried ſome under Ground alive; and now we hear they have new Orders to Burn 18 Villages more thereabouts. At <hi>Spiers</hi> they perſwaded the People to bring their beſt Goods into the great Cathedral Church (under pretence that they had orders not to burn it) which when they had ſo done, they Stole and Plunder'd all; then Burnt the Cathedral, City, and all to the Ground, as alſo the Biſhops Palace. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Canons and Prebends of the ſaid Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral a Foot, they drove before a Troop of Horſe as Priſoners of War to <hi>Landaw;</hi> though the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop was eſteemed a Man of ſingular Piety, Age, and Noble Family; but the Biſhop of <hi>Worms</hi> had a worſe Fate than all that, for he hoping to preſerve his Cathedral, went to ſay high Maſs at the Altar, expoſing the Euchariſt, thinking that the French would not prophane or commit Sacriledge: but after the Soldiers had ſeverely cudgel'd him (though a Man of 80 Years of Age) they caſt him and his Breaden God upon a Cart, and carried him Priſoner to <hi>Landaw,</hi> to his Brother <hi>Collegue.</hi> And now very lately they came to a place called <hi>Loſheim,</hi> in which place they had been drinking the day before, Plundered and Murthered all Men, Women and Children, and thoſe in the very Cradle, Burning the Town to the Ground. At <hi>Francfort</hi> they brought in three Incendiaries, which were ſent out by the French to burn the Imperial Camp. And in <hi>Upper Hungary,</hi> as <hi>Ternaw,</hi> they caught three of them which had ſet the Town a Fire (being ſent out by <hi>Teckley,</hi> who doth no great matter ſince his Wounds at <hi>Clodova,</hi> or <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigrad</hi>) but they gave them their due reward, cutting of each a Finger at 10 diſtant places in the Town, afterwards caſt them in thoſe Flames alive, which they had kindled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Landerlu.</speaker>
               <p>Po! Po! that is nothain, the King de <hi>Fronce</hi> doth act by Maxime of State, he is a grand Monarch, and being in League with <hi>Teck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> muſt ſend him ſome of his Stoakers, as well as he has done Money and Officers; he ſo do thing, <hi>alla Merveille,</hi> that <hi>Hermanſtad</hi> and <hi>Croonſtad</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the two chiefeſt Cities) and <hi>Onoth</hi> in <hi>Tranſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania</hi> are burnt to the Ground, and no Body knows who has done it.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:51965:2"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Democritus.</speaker>
               <p>Certainly, if ever there was a Tophet prepared for a King, <hi>Louis</hi> XIV. will have a great place there; and as the Woman ſaid of her Husb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, of his Loving Fire, ſo God grant him (that which he Loves) enough of it; but I hope the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> &amp;c. will ſtop his Proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dings, the former is paſſed the <hi>Rhine</hi> with 7 Regiments, above <hi>Coblents,</hi> and they are followed by a great many more: 3000 Men from <hi>Juliers,</hi> are on their March to Join them, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Confederate Forces in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorate of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llogn,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re the ſame way in a Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that it is believed, they will Beſiege <hi>Hon</hi> and <hi>Mont Royal,</hi> both at once, which will give him imploy another way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Landerlu.</speaker>
               <p>You are miſtaken, we have News that the King de <hi>France</hi> has demanded 140000 Crowns of the Burgers and Citizens of <hi>Mentz;</hi> and that 100 Waggons are coming to fetch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all the beſt <hi>Rheniſh</hi> Wines away, and the great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non is already removing; and after the Burgers have given all they can by way of Contribution, the King de <hi>France</hi> will ſhew them his pretty <hi>French</hi> trick, to plunder their Houſes, and burn the City to the Ground.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſtus.</speaker>
               <p>It is certainly confirmed, that there is ſuch a horrible Order come out of <hi>France.</hi> That as ſoon as the <hi>Germans</hi> are paſſed the <hi>Rhine,</hi> to burn <hi>Ments;</hi> tho the Electoral Seat; and the City <hi>Landaw,</hi> and all other Cities, Town, and Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to <hi>Straſborg:</hi> Nay, ſome doubt if <hi>Strasborg</hi> it ſelf will not be ſo ſerved, if the Popes Nunclo can ingage the <hi>Romiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> C. Cantons</hi> to caſt off the Neutrality, for the Governors (Monſieur <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millys</hi>) Wife is removing already her beſt Goods, and Houſhold Furnitures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Landerlu.</speaker>
               <p>The King de <hi>France</hi> is of that Fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Policy, that he has already blinded them of Succeſs, eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Solithurn,</hi> and <hi>Sweits</hi> Cantons, that they have given Permiſſion to raiſe 4000 Men, ſo that the <hi>French</hi> Piſtol do out do the Canon of the <hi>Vatican</hi> and that ſhining <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ettal is more effications to thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Suiſſers, than the Holy Fathers Admonition or Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Democritus.</speaker>
               <p>It is pity to ſee ſo many fine Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Towns laid in Aſhes, ſo that there is not ſo much as a token of any Building left in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> they threaten to burn the Subburbs of <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels;</hi> but the Governor has a watchful Eye upon them, and has made a Declaration to all Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Majors, and other Magiſtrates, to give their Aid and Aſſiſtance to all <hi>French</hi> Diſſerters, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing 2 Ducatons to every Trooper, and a Market Price for each Horſe, and to every Foot, or Diſmounted Dragoon half a Ducaton, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all Subjects belonging to the Empire, to leave the <hi>French</hi> Service, according to the <hi>Imperial Advocatoria,</hi> wherein they are declared Traitors that ſhall continue of that Service. We hear they Deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt in great Numbers, 20 and 30 at a Time, there being an Officer from King <hi>William,</hi> who in a ſhort time Liſted 300 Men, moſt <hi>Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> giving them 8 <hi>d.</hi> a Day. We hear from <hi>Flanders,</hi> that a Party of Lieutenant General <hi>Calvo</hi>'s Horſe, came to a place, called <hi>Cocheim,</hi> near <hi>Gaunt,</hi> were they committed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Out-rages, amongſt others, they entered into a Carpenters Houſe, where there was a poor Old and Lame Chirurgion, called <hi>Robert Smett,</hi> whom they bid to abjure his Allegiance from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> under whom he had ſerved 12 Years, and ſwear for <hi>Lowis</hi> XIV. which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaid, he was but for one God, and one King, upon which, they laid him before a great Fire naked, roaſting him, and he ſtill remaining conſtant, turn'd him, and ſo made a perfect <hi>Lawrence</hi> of him, he dying in leſs than half an Hour after. They Write from <hi>Flanders,</hi> that the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> had ſunk 7 Veſſels, with Stones and Gravel, before the Haven of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> which hinders them from going out or in.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>W. B.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
